Calvert Coggeshall
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Calvert Coggeshall papers
1920-1999, bulk 1965-1989
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Coggeshall, Calvert
1.75 linear feet
The papers of Maine abstract painter and interior designer Calvert Coggeshall measure 1.75 linear feet and date from 1920-1999, with the bulk of the material dating from 1965-1989. They consist of scattered biographical material, personal and business related correspondence, writings, exhibition files, design business files, printed material, and photographs of Coggeshall, his friends, and his work.
Provenance
The papers of Calvert Coggeshall were donated in 2006 by his son Tomlin Coggeshall.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Calvert Coggeshall (1907-1990) worked as an abstract painter and interior designer primarily in Maine and New York City. From 1951 to 1978, he exhibited regularly with the Betty Parsons Gallery.
Born in Whitesboro, New York, Coggeshall started his career as an interior designer, working on commissions for clients in the New York City area. He later consulted on the interior designs for Henry Dreyfuss' line of cruise/cargo ships called American Export, popular from the 1940s through the 1960s. In the 1940s, he also worked with inventor Arthur Young to design interiors for the first full-sized scale of Bell helicopter models. By the 1950s, Coggeshall began splitting his time between painting and design work, though he continued to regularly consult and work on several architectural and interior design projects throughout the 1980s.
As a painter, his early monochromatic abstracts were influenced by his friend and abstract expressionist, Bradley Walker Tomlin. An early member of Betty Parson's stable of painters, Coggeshall was friends with other artists, including Jack Tworkov, Grace Hartigan, Katherine Kuh, Nora Sayre, Hedda Sterne, and Richard Tuttle. After summering and eventually moving to Newcastle, Maine in the 1960s, he began introducing color into his abstract paintings. and A major retrospective of his work was held at the Bowdoin College Museum of Art in Maine in 1977. In 1978, he received a Guggenheim fellowship in recognition of his work. Working out of his studios in Newcastle and Manhattan, Coggeshall continued producing abstract paintings into the late 1980s. Coggeshall died in 1990.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Maine abstract painter and designer Calvert Coggeshall measure 1.75 linear feet and date from 1920-1999, with the bulk of the material dating from 1965-1989. They consist of biographical material, personal and business correspondence, personal writings, exhibition and business files, printed material, and photographs. The bulk of the material documents Coggeshall's professional work and his friendships with other artists.
Biographical material includes Coggeshall's personal address books and day planning notes, oral history transcripts, including an interview discussing his friendship with Walker Evans, a copy of his Guggenheim application and acceptance letters, and miscellaneous records.
Correspondence is predominantly in the form of cards, postcards, and short letters received from family and friends. These include correspondence from Coggeshall's father, children, his older grandchildren, and his mother-in-law, Frances Coralie Perkins. Other frequent correspondents include family friend Daphne Cox, artists Michael Lekakis, Loren McIver, Jack Tworkov, and museum director Gordon Washburn.
Personal writings consist of poetry notes and drafts and a short essay on church design.
Exhibition files concern Coggeshall's one man shows at the Betty Parsons Gallery during the 1970s and early 1980s, his retrospective at Bowdoin College in 1977, and his inclusion in shows at Artists Space, the Farnsworth Museum, and Jack Tilton Gallery.
Business files related to Coggeshall's interior design work consist of architectural renderings and blueprints, work proposals, invoices, and receipts. Some of the more significant projects include work done for Lisa de Kooning, Priscilla Morgan, Arthur Penn, and Shoji Sadao.
Printed material includes newspaper clippings, exhibition announcements from other artists, and a booklet showcasing abstract artists titled, "Artfully Taught."
Photographs are color and black and white prints of Coggeshall and his friends in his studio and outside his Newcastle, Maine residence. There are also black and white photographs of Coggeshall's early design work in furniture and fabric, as well as documentation of his gallery design work for the Albright Art Gallery.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1960-1990 (Box 1, OV 3; 8 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1920-1993 (Box 1, OV 3; 28 folders)
Series 3: Writings, 1965-1989 (Box 1; 5 folders)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1970-1992 (Box 1, OV 3; 12 folders)
Series 5: Business Files, 1973-1989 (Boxes 1-2, OV 4-5; 27 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1950-1999 (Box 2, OV 3; 6 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, 1940-1985 (Box 2; 6 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Evans, Walker, 1903-1975; Morgan, Priscilla; Penn, Arthur, 1922-; Shoji, Sadao, 1937-; Artists Space (Gallery); Betty Parsons Gallery; Bowdoin College, Museum of Art; Jack Tilton Gallery; William A. Farnsworth Library and Art Museum
Subjects-Topical:
Artists' studios -- Photographs; Designers -- Maine; Interior decorators -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- Maine; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Poets -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Architectural drawings; Blueprints; Drafts (documents); Essays; Notes; Oral histories (document genres); Photographs; Poems; Transcripts
Names:
Lekakis, Michael, 1907-; Perkins, Frances; Tworkov, Jack; Washburn, Gordon B. (Gordon Bailey), 1904-
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1960-1990, Series 1:; (Box 1, OV 3; 8 folders)
  Biographical material includes Coggeshall's personal address books and day planning notes, his birth certificate and obituary, and a copy of his Guggenheim application and acceptance letters. There are also two oral history transcripts, the first concerning Coggeshall's life and dual career as a painter and designer, the second concerning his friendship with Walker Evans. The interviewers for each oral history are identified as W.B. and N.S. respectively, and may have been conducted by close friends Wally Barker and Nora Sayers. Also included are the records of his Manhattan home renovation project from 1975-1981.
  - Address Book, circa 1960-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birth Certificate, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Guggenheim Fellowship, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Home Renovation, Notes and Receipts, 1975-1981, (Oversized material housed in OV 3) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Interview Transcript, Coggeshall Oral History, circa 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Interview Transcript, Coggeshall re. Walker Evans, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Obituary, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Home Renovation Blueprints and Renderings, 1975-1981, (Oversized material from Box 1, F4) (Box OV 3)
- Correspondence, 1920-1993, Series 2:; (Box 1, OV 3; 28 folders)
  Correspondence is predominantly in the form of cards, postcards, and short letters received from family and friends. These include informal letters and cards from Coggeshall's father, children, his older grandchildren, and his mother-in-law, Frances Coralie Perkins. Other frequent correspondents include family friend Daphne Cox, artists Michael Lekakis, Loren McIver, Jack Tworkov, and museum director Gordon Washburn. Additional correspondents include Walter Barker, Mrs. Alfred J. Barr (Marga), Chouteau Chapin, Nancy Grove, Grace Hartigan, Katherine Kuh, Nora Sayre, Hedda Sterne, Jack Tilton, Richard Tuttle, and Catherine Viviano. A handful of business letters related to Coggeshall's paintings and representation in galleries are also included in the series.
  Correspondence is arranged into 3 subseries:
  Subseries 2.1: Business, 1967-1993
  Subseries 2.2: Family, 1920-1989
  Subseries 2.3: Friends, 1954-1991
  - Business, 1967-1993, Subseries 2.1:
    - Letters Received, Fine Arts Related, 1967-1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Family, 1920-1989, Subseries 2.2:
    - Coggeshall, Howard W., circa 1920-1930, 1935, 1939, (Oversized material housed in OV 3) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Coggeshall, John, Kate, Pleasance, and Tomlin, 1969-1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Daniel, Kirstin, and Zoe, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Perkins, Frances, circa 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Oversized Clipping, 1946, (Oversized material from Box 1, F9) (Box OV 3)
  - Friends, 1954-1991, Subseries 2.3:
    - A, Miscellaneous, 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Alain
      Alice
      Alison
      Alison and George
      Anna
      Ardis
    - B, Miscellaneous, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Barker, Walter W.
      Barnes, Kate
      Barr, Mrs. Alfred J. (Marga)
      Batine
      Berry, Joyce
      Bewin, Bruce and Naomi
      Bill
      Binnings, Robin
      Breit, Alice Morris
      Brown, Amelia
    - Cox, Daphne, 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - C, Miscellaneous, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Chapin, Chouteau
      Chris
      Clara and Bill
      Claude
      Coolidge, Helen
    - D, Miscellaneous, 1954-1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Dache, Lilly
      De Kooning, Lisa
      De Menil, J.
      Dennie
      Diddy
      Donald
    - E-G, Miscellaneous, 1955-1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Emory
      Flora
      Frencher, Peter
      Gifford, Pete and Marie
      Glidden, Arthur B.
      Grove, Nancy
      Gwyn
    - H, Miscellaneous, 1970-1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      H
      Haggin, Bernard
      Hal
      Hall, Lee
      Hartigan, Grace
      Holme, Frida
      Holt, John and Elizabeth
      Houghton, Betty
    - I-K, Miscellaneous, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Itami, Michi
      Izumi, Mihoko
      Jane
      Kramer, Roz
      Kuh, Katherine
    - Lekakis, Michael, 1948-1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - L, Miscellaneous, 1966-1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      LaF.O., W.
      Lenore
      Leslie, Anne, Seaver, and Genevieve
      Lily
      Lindlay, Frances
      Lippard, Peg
      Lise
    - MacIver, Loren, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - M, Miscellaneous, 1966-1982 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      M
      M, Dorothy
      Marian and Louis
      Matisse, Pierre
      McRise, Paul
      Mellen, Constance
    - N-O, Miscellaneous, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Nancy and Bob
      Natasha
      Nicholson, Bettina
      Noguchi, Isamu
      Oliver, Harriet
    - P, Miscellaneous, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      P., E.
      Pelletur, Brenda
      Peterson, Dorothy
      Potter, Alice
      Priscilla
    - R, Miscellaneous, 1954-1988 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Rankin, V.
      Reichek, Jessie
      Rikur
      Ritcha, Jane
      Rossie
      Russell
    - S, Miscellaneous, 1975-1991 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      S., Jane
      Sadao, Tsuneko
      Sayre, Nora
      Shemi, Y.
      Silberman, John
      Sims, Henry
      Stehli, Annabelle
      Sterne, Hedda
    - Tworkov, Jack and Wally, 1967-1982 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - T, Miscellaneous, 1966-1990 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      T.
      Taylor, Emily
      Tilton, Jack
      Tuttle, Richard
    - U-V, Miscellaneous, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      U., J.B.
      Valerie
      Viviano, Catherine
    - Washburn, Gordon, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Y, Miscellaneous, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Yvonne
    - Unidentified Correspondents, circa 1965-1989 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Writings, 1965-1989, Series 3:; (Box 1; 5 folders)
  Personal writings consist of a short essay, "A Christmas Church" and numerous poetry drafts and notes. One series of seven poems, "Seven" is typewritten.
  - Essay, "A Christmas Church," circa 1965-1985 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Notes, circa 1965-1989 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Poetry, "Seven," 1976 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Poetry, Drafts, circa 1965-1989 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Poetry, Notebook, circa 1965-1989 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Exhibition Files, 1970-1992, Series 4:; (Box 1, OV 3; 12 folders)
  Exhibition files include photographs, correspondence, announcements, and lists related to Coggeshall's one man shows at the Betty Parsons Gallery during the 1970s and early 1980s and his retrospective at Bowdoin College in 1977. The Bowdoin retrospective also include blueprints of the gallery space and Coggeshall's notations on the planned layout of his works. Additional correspondence regarding his inclusion in shows at Artists Space, the Farnsworth Museum, and Jack Tilton Gallery are also included in the series.
  - Announcement Lists, circa 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Artists Space, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Betty Parsons Gallery, 1970-1982, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 42-46)
  - Bowdoin College, 1977, (2 folders; Oversized material housed in OV 3) (Box 1, Folder 47-48)
  - Farnsworth Museum, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Jack Tilton Gallery, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Oversize Blueprints and Renderings, 1977, (Oversized material from Box 1, F48) (Box OV 3)
- Business Files, 1973-1989, Series 5:; (Boxes 1-2, OV 4-5; 27 folders)
  Business files related to Coggeshall's interior design work consist of his client and contractor address book, architectural renderings and blueprints, work proposals, lists, invoices, and receipts. Some of the more significant projects include apartment design renovations for Lisa de Kooning, Priscilla Morgan, Arthur Penn, Shoji Sadao, Richard Lombard, and John Silberman.
  Projects are generally in the following order: blueprints, estimates, payment, notes, receipts, and invoices.
  - Address Book, circa 1973-1989 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Client Blueprints, Miscellaneous, circa 1973-1985, (Oversized material housed in OV 4) (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Client Invoices, 1973-1988 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Day Planning Notes, circa 1973-1985 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Brown, Kate, circa 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Davidson, Joan, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - de Kooning, Lisa, 1983-1989, (2 folders; Oversized material housed in OV 4) (Box 1, Folder 57-58)
  - Gunther, Jane, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Hall, Naomi, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Lombard, Richard, 1983-1986, (3 folders; Oversized material housed in OV 4) (Box 1, Folder 61-63)
  - Lombard, Richard, 1983-1984, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Lurie, Jerome, 1984-1985, (Oversized material housed in OV 4) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Morgan, Priscilla, 1982-1984, (Oversized material housed in OV 4) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Penn, Arthur, 1984, (Oversized material housed in OV 5) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Rockefeller University, 1973-1974, (Oversized material housed in OV 5) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sadao, Shoji, 1983-1988, (Oversized material housed in OV 5) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Silberman, John, 1986-1988, (3 folders; Oversized material housed in OV 5) (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - Oversize Blueprints and Renderings1983-1989, (Oversized material from Box 1, F52, F57-58, F61 and Box 2, F5-6) (Box OV 4)
  - Oversize Blueprints and Renderings1973-1988, (Oversized material from Box 2, F7-9, F11) (Box OV 5)
- Printed Material, 1950-1999, Series 6:; (Box 2, OV 3; 6 folders)
  Printed material includes newspaper clippings reviewing Coggeshall's work, exhibition announcements from other artists, including Lyonel Feininger, Moy Glidden, Ken Greenleaf, David Plowden, and Jack Tworkov. A booklet showcasing abstract artists sponsored by the New York Governor's office titled, "Artfully Taught" is also included in the series.
  - Exhibition Announcements, Other Artists, 1950-1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Booklet, "Artfully Taught," 1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, Coggeshall Art, 1968-1992, (Oversized material housed in OV 3) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, Coggeshall Design, 1944, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Oversize Clippings, 1967, 1969, 1977, (Oversized material from Box 2, F15) (Box OV 3)
- Photographs, 1940-1985, Series 7:; (Box 2; 6 folders)
  Photographs include color and black and white prints of Coggeshall and his friends in his studio and outside his Newcastle, Maine residence. There are also black and white photographs of Coggeshall's early design work in furniture and fabric, as well as documentation of his gallery design work for the Albright Art Gallery.
  A list of additional photographs in the collection can be found in Folder 18.
  - Coggeshall, Artwork and Studio, 1964-1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Coggeshall, Friends of, circa 1960-1985 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Coggeshall, Maine Residence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Design, Albright Art Gallery, circa 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Design, Fabric, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Design, Tables, Chairs, and Lamps, circa 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 23)